"Flushing Calories with Fiber for Weight Loss"
Fiber seems so, well, boring.
It's not one
of the nutrition topics
commonly placed
among cutting-edge research.
By definition,
fiber is indigestible,
can't be absorbed
into the body.
So, it just stays in our gut
to bulk up our stool.
This is not to belittle
the importance
of bowel regularity.
Constipation is a global issue.
In the United States,
for example,
chronic idiopathic constipation
impacts 5% of people.
If even half
of the adult U.S. population
ate three more grams
of fiber a day,
a quarter cup (50-60g)
of cooked beans,
or a bowl of oatmeal,
we could relieve
enough constipation
to save billions of dollars
in medical costs annually.
But it's not like we thought
fiber really did anything.
In fact, you can get
the same laxative effect
with indigestible
plastic particles.
Feeding people
a couple spoonfuls
of sliced polyvinyl tubing,
not recommended,
ends up increasing
their stool bulk, frequency,
and softening the consistency.
So, for decades,
fiber was viewed
as a similarly inert,
indigestible substance.
We've since moved beyond
fiber's classic function
as an anti-constipation agent
to recognizing
its other beneficial effects,
including the many ways
it can facilitate weight loss.
The first major review,
"Dietary Fiber
and Weight Regulation,"
based on a dozen
interventional studies
where people were randomized
into higher
or lower fiber diets,
found that the additional
consumption
of 14 grams of fiber a day
led to an average weight loss
of 4 pounds (1.8 kg)
over 3.8 months.
That's only about
a pound (0.45 kg) a month,
but the weight loss was greater
among those with excess weight.
Study participants
with overweight or obesity
lost triple the weight
compared to lean individuals.
And 14 grams of fiber
isn't a lot.
That would even take
the average U.S. diet
up to the recommended
minimum average
adequate daily fiber intake
of 38 grams for men
and 25 daily grams for women.
The increased fiber intake
appeared to lead
to about a 10% drop
in daily calorie intake.
Why would more fiber
mean fewer calories?
Well, conventionally,
fiber is considered
to have zero calories.
So, it adds bulk to food
without adding extra calories,
resulting in a lower
"energy-to-weight ratio"
in the food.
To illustrate,
let's compare a food
to its fiber-depleted
equivalent.
Consider a bottle
of cold-pressed apple juice.
That's basically just an apple
with its fiber removed.
You could drink a regular bottle
of juice
(about 15 ounces, 445 ml)
in a matter of seconds.
But to get the same number
of calories,
you'd have to eat nearly 5 cups
(550-600 g) of apple slices.
First, you'd have to chew
all those apple slices.
Fiber-rich foods
require more chewing,
which slows down eating rate,
which itself can
improve satiety.
That also allows
for more secretion of saliva
and stomach juices.
Researchers spread
a barium paste
onto slices of different kinds
of bread.
Talk about research
that would not
pass human safety review today,
and found that on x-ray,
the stomach shadow was larger
after eating whole wheat bread
compared to white.
Five grams
of a highly viscous fiber,
like what's in apples and oats,
can hold approximately
a quart of water (945 ml)
as it passes through
the stomach and small intestine.
So, that's having
an extra two pounds (0.9 kg)
of zero-calorie food mass
filling you up.
If you feed people
the same meal,
one with natural fiber
(whole wheat pasta
with pureed veggies and fruits)
and the other meal
composed of the same foods
with the fiber depleted
(white bread with fruit
and vegetable juices),
but both meals
have the same volume,
the stomach empties faster
with the fiber-depleted meal,
about 45 minutes faster.
It's not what we eat,
but what we absorb.
So, we can lose more weight
on a high-fiber diet
eating the exact same number
of calories,
because some of the calories
get trapped
and never make it
into our system.
Those on a standard
American diet
lose about 5% of the calories
they eat in their waste.
A higher-fiber diet
can double that.
It's not just that the calories
in high-fiber foods
are less available to absorb.
They trap calories
across the board.
Feed people whole meal bread
versus white bread,
and stool analyses find
that we flush more calories
on the whole meal bread.
Eat a Twinkie
on a high-fiber diet
and absorb
fewer Twinkie calories.
It's like every
calorie label you read
gets instantly discounted
on a high-fiber diet.
Most nutrition classes
will teach
that a gram of protein
has four calories,
a gram of fat has nine calories,
and a gram of carbs has four.
But that's only on a typical
low-fiber diet.
On a higher-fiber diet,
up around the average
of those eating
strictly plant-based diets,
the effective calorie counts
per gram drop from 4, 9, 4,
for protein, fat,
and carbs, respectively,
to around 3.5, 8.7, 3.8.
That may not seem like a lot,
but if Americans just reached
the minimum recommended
fiber intake,
that might decrease
calorie absorption
by more than 100 calories a day.
That may be enough to prevent
that average gradual
annual weight gain
most experience
through middle age.
Even a small change
in daily calorie absorption
could have
long-term significance
for weight management.